Guide to the Alvah Bessie Papers ALBA.024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alvah Bessie Papers
1936-1985, (Bulk 1936-1939; 1967-1985)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985
ALBA.024
3.25 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes and 1 folder in an oversize shared box
Alvah Bessie (1904-1985) was an author and screenwriter who fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, and was later blacklisted as one of the "Hollywood Ten" cited for contempt of Congress for refusing to answer questions at the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) hearings on the influence of the Communist Party in the motion-picture industry. This collection chiefly documents Bessie’s activities and writings related to the Spanish Civil War, and his affiliation with the Veterans with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). Included are the hand-written journals kept by Bessie during his 11 months of service in Spain from January through December 1938, military documents, a working draft of his memoir Men in Battle, and the typescript of Spain Again. This collection also contains subject files pertaining to the Bay Area Chapter VALB, and materials related to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade anthology Bessie was engaged in editing at the time of his death.
Provenance
The bulk of the material was purchased by Bruce Rubenstein and donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in July 1994. Alvah Bessie’s son Dan donated additional materials in November 1994.This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alvah Bessie was born in New York City on June 4, 1904 to Daniel Nathan Cohen Bessie, a successful businessman and inventor, and Adeline Schlesinger. The younger of two boys, Bessie was raised in ease in the then-prosperous precincts of Harlem. He attended public school, graduated from Dewitt Clinton High School and, in 1920, enrolled in Columbia University. Bessie's rebellious nature often placed him at odds with his father's conservative values and authoritarian manner. When, in 1922, Daniel Bessie died after suffering a severe economic setback, he left his family in a precarious financial state, but Alvah Bessie free to pursue his own ambitions. Bessie completed his degree and graduated from Columbia in 1924 with a B.A. in English. Through a friend, he found work as an actor with Eugene O'Neill's Provincetown Players. For the next four years Bessie immersed himself in the New York theater scene, performing with the Provincetown Players, the Theatre Guild and with actor-manager Walter Hampden's repertory company in a production of Cyrano de Bergerac. Recognizing his limited talent as an actor, he left the theater and, in 1928, traveled to France to join the community of American expatriates in Paris intent on becoming a writer.
During his brief stay in France, he worked as a rewrite man at the Paris-Times, and wrote "Redbird," his first short story to receive publication. He returned to New York in 1929, and for the next six years, his stories, essays, and reviews appeared in The New Republic, Scribner's, Atlantic Monthly, Saturday Review of Literature, Collier's and Story. In July 1930, he married Mary Burnett, a puppet-maker and artist. The couple moved to Vermont and had two boys -- Daniel and David. Bessie began work on his first novel, Dwell in the Wilderness. During this time, Bessie also began to study Marxist theory and question his political convictions. Bessie was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship following the publication of his novel in 1935, and, with his family, returned to New York. Back in the City, Bessie began to move in more radical circles, and in 1936 he became a member of the Communist Party. In 1935 he joined the staff of the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, serving as drama and book editor. His tenure at the paper was marked by dissent. His radical stance on striking maritime workers in 1936 and on the Spanish Civil War ran counter to management's more conservative views. A final dispute with the paper stemmed from his praise of French novelist and aviator Andre Malraux's efforts to organize a squadron of French flyers to aid the Spanish Republic. In 1937 he resigned from the Eagle and went to work in the public relations office of the Spanish Information Bureau, a New York agency of the Republican Government. During this period, the Bessies' marriage began to founder. The couple separated and soon after divorced.
On January 22, 1938, Bessie sailed to Spain on the S.S. Lafayette to join the International Brigade's fight against the Franco-led rebellion. Although he earned his pilot's license before leaving for Spain with the objective of serving as a flyer, he was assigned to a front-line combat unit with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, participating in the Ebro offensive from July to September 1938, and attaining the rank of sergeant-adjutant. He also served as a correspondent for the International Brigade's publication The Volunteer for Liberty. He daily chronicled his personal experiences in a series of notebooks, and upon his return to the United States, these jottings became the basis of his wartime memoirs, Men in Battle(1939). From 1939 to 1943, Bessie was film and theatre critic for the New Masses, and, under a pseudonym, wrote a regular column for a Young Communist League publication. He remained active in the Spanish Republican cause, working on behalf of the Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee writing articles and delivering speeches.
In 1943 he moved to California and started writing screenplays when Warner Brothers studios hired him as a contract writer. During World War II, he served as Second Lieutenant in the Civil Air Patrol, Los Angeles Squadron 3. In 1945 his original story that was the basis for the screenplay of "Objective Burma" was nominated for an Academy Award. His other screen credits from this time include, "Hotel Berlin," "The Very Thought of You," "Northern Pursuit, " and "Smart Woman." He was fired from Warner Brothers in 1945 in the wake of his outspoken support of striking studio workers. In September 1947, the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) launched an investigation on the influence of the Communist Party in the motion-picture industry. Over fifty people were called to testify and answer questions regarding political affiliations and associations. Bessie, along with nine other Hollywood figures, refused to comply with the Committee's demands. They were cited for contempt of Congress, given one-year prison sentences, and became known as the "Hollywood Ten." Bessie served out his term in a federal correctional facility in Texarkana, Texas and was blacklisted in Hollywood.
After his release from prison, Bessie was not able to get work in the film industry or elsewhere in Los Angeles, so he relocated to San Francisco and found employment with the International Longshoremen's and Warehouseman's Union as assistant editor of the union's newspaper, The Dispatcher. In 1951 he edited, The Heart of Spain, an anthology of writings on the Spanish Civil War published and distributed by the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He worked as stage manager and lighting technician for the hungry i nightclub (1956-1963), an experience that inspired the novel, One for My Baby(1980), and as a cultural critic on the People's Daily World (1957-1960), sometimes using a pseudonym. In the mid-1960s, he worked briefly as a publicist for several San Francisco arts organizations, including the San Francisco Mime Troupe and the San Francisco Film Festival.
Alvah Bessie married Sylviane Martin in 1963. (Martin was his third wife; his second marriage, to Helen Clare Nelson, ended in divorce). In 1968, Bessie collaborated on the Spanish film, Espana otra vez, and offered an account of the production and his return to Spain in his memoir Spain Again. He remained active in the Bay Area Chapter of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and was honored, in 1975, at their 39th Anniversary Dinner. Before he could complete work on Our Fight, a VALB anthology devoted to the writings of Lincoln Brigade veterans, Bessie died of a heart attack on July 21, 1985, at the age of 81.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Spanish Civil War:
Subseries A.: Documents, Undated; 1938.
This series contains documents related to Bessie's activities during the Spanish Civil War. Notable are the four hand-written journals in which Bessie kept a record of his 11 months of service in Spain from January through December 1938. A typed transcription of these journals is available here as well. (These journals were published posthumously by his son Dan Bessie in 2001). In addition to a range of military documents, and Bessie's repatriation papers, this series includes propaganda leaflets distributed by the Fascist forces (in Spanish with annotated English translations) that were intended to demoralize the Republican troops.
Series I: Spanish Civil War:
Subseries B. Artifacts, Undated; 1938; 1976.
The artifacts in the series are mementos from Spain and commemorative objects that Bessie acquired following the war. Of particular interest are the corporal's stripes and International Brigade insignia from Bessie's uniform.
Series II: Writings, 1939; 1946-1984.
This series includes a working draft of Men in Battle, and typescript of Spain Again. Notable is Bessie's 1972 treatment of "The Volunteers," a screenplay based on the life and death of James Lardner, a volunteer who was killed in action during the final days of foreign participation in the Spanish Civil War. Bessie, Lincoln Brigade veteran Arthur Landis, and Bessie's son Dan, later reworked the script, renamed it "The Volunteer," and unsuccessfully sought to have the project produced. Correspondence between the three collaborators and revisions related to this project are located in this series. Also included are the texts of three speeches delivered by Bessie in the 1940s on the plight of Spanish refugees.
Series III: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Anthology, Undated; 1937-1939; 1967-1985.
This series includes materials related to the VALB anthology that Bessie was engaged in editing at the time of his death. Originally titled "The Good Fight," the anthology was published after Bessie's death as Our Fight under the editorship of Albert Prago. The anthology, which was intended as a fiftieth anniversary publication, was chiefly devoted to veterans' accounts of their experiences during and after the war. The bulk of this series is made up of submissions from veterans for this project. Many of these writings are photocopies or transcriptions of previously published works. However, some notable exceptions include a transcription of David Gordon's diary written in 1939 following his release from a Fascist prisoner of war camp; an excerpted memoir by Arthur Timpson; and three essays written by Ben Iceland shortly after his return from Spain. Some of these submissions include correspondence. This series also includes a prospectus for the anthology and general correspondence and notes related to this project.
Series IV: Subject Files, 1936-1985.
This series includes materials related to Bessie's activities the Bay Area Chapter of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Spanish Civil War anniversaries and symposia, and correspondence with veterans, much of which relates to the VALB anthology. A letter from Steven Nelson offers an account of escorting Lillian Hellman and Dorothy Parker through Valencia in the fall of 1937. Some notable materials in this series include a copy of a letter from Ernest Hemingway to Milton Wolff related to their falling out over For Whom the Bell Tolls; inscribed reprints from Robert Rosenstone; promotional material and correspondence generated by Bessie related to screenings of the documentary "To Die in Madrid"; and correspondence, clippings and speeches from the 1975 VALB tribute to Bessie. The series also contains Bessie's membership cards from VALB, the American Newspaper Guild, and the Screenwriters Guild.
Arrangement
Series I, Arranged alphabetically within Subseries. Series II, Arranged alphabetically by genre (article, books, essays, screenplays, etc.) and than alphabetically by title. Series III and IV are arranged alphabetically.
Organized into four series:
Missing Title
I. Spanish Civil War
II. Writings, 1939; 1946-1984.
III. Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Anthology, Undated; 1937-1939; 1967-1985.
IV. Subject Files, 1936-1985.
Related Material
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Alvah Bessie Papers, 1929-1985. Wisconsin Historical Society. U.S. Mss 59AN.
James Lardner Papers, ALBA #67.
Arthur H. Landis Papers, ALBA #66
Separated Material
Photographs from the Alvah Bessie Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Biography.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Drafts (documents); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Literature and the war.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Poetry.; Speeches.; Ebro River, Battle of the, Spain, 1938.; Correspondence.; Biography files.; Articles.; Lardner, James, 1914-1938; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986; Bessie, Dan.; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Wolff, Milton.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Iceland, Benjamin, 1910-1990; Rosenstone, Robert A.; Timpson, Arthur; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee; Gordon, David, 1909-1973
- Series I: Spanish Civil War, 1938-1976
  - Subseries I:A: Documents, 1938
    - Carnet de Honor, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Carnet Mititar, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Certificate of Service, November 10, 1938 (Box MSOS006)
    - Citation of Honor (Signed Certificates with Color Graphics), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Fascist Propaganda Leaflets (In Spanish with English Translations), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ibarruri, Dolores ("La Pasionaria"): Farewell Address to the International Brigades, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - International Brigade Leaflet (Dropped by Planes during Barcelona Parade), Oct 29, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Journal #1 (Handwritten), Jan 22, 1938-Apr 15, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Journal #2 (Handwritten), Apr 10, 1938-Jul 26, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Journal #3 (Handwritten), Jul 27, 1938-Sep 7, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Journal #4 (Handwritten) and Blotter, Oct 5, 1938-Dec 4, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Journals #1-4 (Typescript), Jan 22, 1938-Dec 4, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lopoff, Aaron: Condolence Letter, Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mess Allowance Receipt, Nov 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Order for Promotion, Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Orders from the Commissariat, Sep 23, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Repatriation Papers, Nov 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Salvoconducto (Safe Conduct Pass) and Annotated Expense Report, Sep 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries I:B: Artifacts, 1938; 1976
    - Belt, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Commemorative Figurine: Catalan Boy, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Flag: International Brigade (4"x 6"), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Key Ring: Fortieth International Brigade Souvenir, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Military Patches: International Brigade Insignia and Corporal Stripes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series II: Writings, 1939; 1946-1984
  - Article: "Reunion in Florence", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Book: Men in Battle, Original Working Draft, pp. 1-107 (Includes introductory note by Dan Bessie), 1939, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Book: Men in Battle, Original Working Draft, pp. 108-175, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Book: Men in Battle, Original Working Draft, pp. 176-254, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Book: Men in Battle, Original Working Draft, pp. 255-291, plus index and inserts, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Book: Spain Again: Front Matter (typescript) pp. 1-100, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Book: Spain Again(Photocopied typescript) pp. 1-100, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Book: Spain Again(Photocopied typescript) pp. 101-234, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Book: Spain Again(Photocopied typescript) pp. 235-283, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Essay: "Hesitation Waltz" (Edited Draft), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Eulogy: In Memory of Frieda Wolff, from The Volunteer, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Poem: "For My Dead Brother," a Tribute to Aaron Lapoff (Published in Masses and Mainstream), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Screenplay: "The Volunteer": Correspondence and Revisions, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Screenplay: "The Volunteer": Outline by A. Bessie and Arthur Landis, ca.1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Screenplay: "The Volunteers": Treatment, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Speech: Fascism and Spain: Delivered in San Francisco and Los Angeles, 1946, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Speech: Spanish Refugee Appeal, Nov 1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Speech: Spanish Refugee Appeal, May 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series III: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Anthology, 1937-1939; 1967-1985
  - Amery, Al: Memoir (Excerpts) and Poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Anthology: Correspondence and Notes, undated, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Anthology: Prospectus, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Anthology: Prospectus, Partial Draft, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Anthology: Rejected from Consideration: Non-Veteran Writings Published between 1936-1944, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bailey, Bill: "Homage to Joe Bianca," Published in The Volunteer, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bailey, Bill: Kid from Hoboken(Excerpt), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bessie, Alvah: "For My Dead Brother," Poem in Tribute to Aarpm Lapoff, Originally Published in Masses and Mainstream, 1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Carsman, Sam: Memoirs (Excerpt), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cloke, Richard: Selected Poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cogswell, Theodore: Biographical Material, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Colodny, Robert: "Corpus Duende" (Excerpted Radio Drama), ca.1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Colodny, Robert: "Spain and Vietnam" (Pamphlet) and remarks on US Relations with Spain, undated, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Crome, Len: "Walter a Soldier in Spain, " (Essay on Karol Swierczewski), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Geiser, Carl: "Prisoners of the Good Fight" (Excerpted transcripts) and Biographical Material., undated, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Geiser, Carl: Spanish Civil War Letters (transcripts), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Gerlach, John R. "Behind Enemy Lines", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Goldring, Benjamin: Articles and Obituaries, undated, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gordon, David: Spanish Civil War Diary (transcript), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Greenspan, Celia and George Marion: Spanish Civil War Correspondence (photocopies), Sep 1939-Aug 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hemingway, Ernest: "On the American Dead in Spain," Originally Published in New Masses(copy), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Iceland, Benjamin: "Almansa" (photocopied typescript), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Iceland, Benjamin: "Big Retreat" (photocopied typescript), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Iceland, Benjamin: "Last Months in Spain" (photocopied typescript), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Iceland, Benjamin: "Teruel" (photocopied typescript), 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Jones, James Moore: Memoirs (Excerpt), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kaufman, Sid: Edited Spanish Civil War Diary and Oral History Excerpts (Published in The Volunteer), 1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lardner, James: Spanish Civil War Correspondence, 1938 (photocopies), undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lending, Edward: "Los Rompedores", undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Manners, Robert: "Letter to Spain," Published in Columbia Poetry, 1939(photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - McCarthy, Bill: Poem, Untitled, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Nelson, Steve: "Doing it the Hard Way," Excerpt from The Volunteers(photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Nelson, Steve: Steve Nelson: American Radical(photocopied excerpt), undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newman, Sol: "Hoax or History: Hugh Thomas’ The Spanish Civil War," Essay (photocopied typescript), undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Percikow, Henri: Poems, 1972-1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Persoff, Jim (Jacob): "Paseo at Villaneuva de Santa Clara", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Prago, Albert: "A Visit with Eight Spanish Woman," Pamphlet (photocopy), undated, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Rolfe, Edwin: Selected Poems, Originally Published in New Masses, 1944 (photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Steck, Robert: Biographical Mateiral on Carmelo Delgado, Leo Grachow, Walter Grant, Albert Ziegler, undated, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Timpson, Arthur: Memoirs (Excerpt), undated, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Wallach, Hy: "Captured by Fascists," Published in The Volunteer, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Watt, George: "Reunion in Hamme", undated, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Weissman, Irving: "The Return," Originally Published in The Massachusetts Review(photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Wesson, Neil: Poems and Biographical Material (photocopied typescript), undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Wolff, Milton: "Remember This, " Essay, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Wolff, Milton: Three Poems, Originally Published in The San Fernando Poetry Journal(photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 1936-1985
  - Allen, Richard Sanders: Spanish Civil War Aviators and Aviation, undated, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - American Participation in the Spanish Civil War, Historiographical Essay, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bessie, Alvah: Membership Cards: American Newspaper Guild, Screenwriters Guild, VALB, 1936-1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Busch, Ernst: Clipping, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - City College Volunteers-in-Spain Memorial Ceremony, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Corpus Duende: Echoes of the Spanish Civil War": Radio Drama with Performances by Eli Wallach, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Amery, Al, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Bailey, Bill, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Cloke, Richard, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Cogswell, Theodore, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Colodny, Robert, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Colow, Maury, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Fishman, Moe, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Gerlach, John, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Goldring, Benjamin, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Grunblatt, Jacques, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Iceland, Benjamin, undated, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Incoming (General), undated, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Landis, Arthur, undated, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Lending, Edward, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Love, Vaughn, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Martin, Fredericka, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Nelson, Steve, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Smorodin, Abe, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Tabb, Herbert (Hy), undated, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 25)